foreign
[Music]
on the 1st of October 2020 and that is
the time where we had an interesting mix
of matrices so that's the time that we
were in the midst of the covet lockdown
we also saw the impact of the AGR crisis
on four we've also seen uh the 5G
Spectrum auctions and then subsequently
the fastest 5G rolled out we've also
seen numerous developments on the
regulatory front to promote growth in
the broadcast industry so it's been an
exciting time Mr vagila thank you so
much for joining us for being a part of
this conversation as we move forward
there is a growing demand within the
Telecom industry uh that look we provide
the network we provide the
infrastructure there should be some
compensation from the Ott players they
should at least compensate us some
formula right now they're not on what
the formula should be like they're only
on the principle in your experience from
the three years from your experience in
some of the other jurisdictions what is
the way for
consumers are getting something you know
free and cheaper you know that they're
not I should you know promote that but
in the last you know five years lot of
things have changed and all over the
world and most of the Telecom operators
they are now claiming that and
and you know and they should be
compensated for no uh you know for
carrying the Ott content so if that
connection uh you know government also
you know a reference back to us and ask
us to do the consultation again and we
have issued our consultation and it's a
very very contitious and very very you
know I would say controversial uh
subject uh uh you know the consultation
is still going on
um uh they had asked for more time and
we are get to do the PHD after OSB at I
will take an appropriate
thank you I think it's a very
interesting answer that you give us in
terms of setting the framework a very
controversial decision uh like you said
but from moving from one controversy to
the other I just want to get a sensor
one of the aspects that defined the
beginning part of your teleop was the
AGR ratio the way it panned out uh there
was a lot of Engagement that the tra had
also done on the subject I just want to
get a sense that when ishti looks back
at this AGR issue you think this is a
battle in your sense as a telecom Titan
this is a battle that the center could
have done without uh in in interest of
the health of the industry
whether we like it or not license fee is
there and the license fees then
constructed easier will be there and now
one of the central question in the you
know the court of law honorable Supreme
Court
and you know they have been accepted the
government in that circumferences you
know we have to see how can you know
further we can work on that so I think
the issues settled there may be some
issues or no what are what should be the
you know part of the easy and which
should not be the part of the Asia
recently DOD has done immensely you know
a very good job by you know giving
further clarification uh so you know the
uh
now the issue with the license fee
whether that is uh very high or it
should it is very you know what should
we learn about that so you know that an
issue I think you know I had to come to
take that lesson is reduced but
government has not accepted that tenant
uh so but you know that that uh license
piece you're at present this day so in
easier definition has been I think you
know uh has been now I think is a lot of
things have been removed most important
the reforms you know it has for example
you know reduce the interest rate right
that is one thing secondly penalty has
been removed
reforms the government has taken and the
kind of uh uh you know actions have been
taken difficulties of the witness has
helped the sector I see
um so you know so so there are some
issues today for example Vodafone for
example you know it has not been able to
implement 5G and for example uh you know
BSN BSNL again has now started Implement
4D with the indigenous technology that
is great thing but there will be now I
think implementing 5G also so their
concern remains that you know BSNL and
uh Vodafone they are not implemented 5G
in what way the competition will span
out and how do we now the you know how
will the subscribers
um Behavior will change the subscribable
page among the videos uh you know
stakeholders
at least fair enough uh you mentioned
sir some concerns that you have with
respect to Vodafone what are the
concerns that the average with respect
the fundraising these questions that I
want to ask in context of the very
recent era recommendations that the NT
barriers need to be done with the bank
guarantees need to be much they need to
be uh it needs to be creating an
environment where it is easy for
investors to come in when you look at
this Vodafone crisis and when you look
at these recommendations you see
interest by investors and Telecom
players on the fringes sitting on the
sidelines wanting a slice of the Indian
Telecom Pride you see that happening see
actually the the there were certain
entry behaviors and government itself
has sent this reference to us that we
should we should be examine the whole
issue so you know we we very we had a
very you know hard thinking on this and
we are asked well tough questions in our
consultation consultant paper there
should there be entry variously approach
there but you know considering because I
think that is this sector is very uh you
know sensitive it has a lot of security
issues also I know we cannot do away
with you know some sort of applications
not that but in some cases we have done
with the application
so I think you know
um if this will according to me and
choose the new investors to come to the
sectors
ISP an EPC and and many other you know
uh you know small uh players and about
that it will be very wealone for them
you know we have reduced the NBC then
you know and then application to Great
extent I think it's only ten percent for
90 we have reduced because compared to
other countries you know VN or somehow
has not become very popular and uh you
know the government and the price
concern is that you know the Vienna
should be there because you know we are
not there you know they will actually
contribute to infrastructure and uh the
the you know Telecom operators who have
the problem of raising Finance maybe the
small NOS of the you know vmosis no they
can actually have been coming out with
the infrastructure and providing the
sufficient you know operators that way
you know the the issue of raising the
tax by the Telecom operator can be
reduced it actually that way you know we
had also we have also recommended you
know unwinding of the network and the
you know Services telephone service in
network and that government is
considering and I think you know so if
that is done again you know uh you know
the the stress on the uh Telecom
operators and again the reduced uh great
and more investors can enter into uh you
know these uh service sector that is
what we believe but you see sort of
active interest by people sitting on the
sidelines wanting to be a part of the
Indian telephone story investors or the
other companies themselves there were
conversations around Verizon the likes
of Amazon wanting a slice of people so
that is that is about space Factor see
let us understand one thing that in
Telecom especially when it comes to the
access and terrestrial you know Network
huge investment is required in form of
you know uh you know fiberization uh
putting towers and ptas and then you
know purchase of the you know purchasing
the Spectrum in addition to our course
you know having you know very
it would not be easy you know for the
you know people to enter the market
unless they are very big people that is
one thing but there are many other you
know service providers where the
possibility first I told about vno or
ISP or for infrastructure provider we
have recently you know recommended uh
you know creating a one category of you
know licensees that is called bcip
digital you know uh connectivity
infrastructure provider here they can
provide even you know active
infrastructure also so there also you
know that will also enthuse lot of
people to enter the market and see let
us let us be very clear so
digitalization of this economy and
Society is here this day
taking place is mind-boggling so for
example you know in DPI number digital
public infrastructure almost 45 percent
of the online transactions every day
right so so digitalization is here to
stay in you know Telecom infrastructure
is key to everything you know
infrastructure network is key to you
know our digitalization quality of the
the economy naturally as the
installation takes place more investors
will
be required the huge demand of the you
know digital
products and these and digital services
so I am very hopeful that more investors
will enter into this Market
let me ask you a question from a
consumer standpoint and I think this has
been one of the most defining features
of your tenure which is UCC the battle
against spam now in our experience from
the consumer experience this is proven
to be some kind of Hydra monster where
you cut one head and there are two heads
that takes its place how do you describe
this journey on the battle against spam
and UCC say spam and UCC this is the
problem which is faced by all the
countries all over the world and we had
organized one regulated conference here
when I completed 25 years and you know
the you know the you know there are huge
challenges One Challenge is that you
know the spammers you know they are one
step ahead always because they also have
access to the technology and they can
use the technology in order to spam in
order to Desert the people and this is a
very big problem you know personally for
example I will also say that you know I
am also put you know a lot of
inconvenience and harassment you know we
also receive a lot of you know SMS and
you know the full course which you don't
want so you know the yearly of that too
I looked into a one is that you know if
uh you know people do need information
on various products and various you know
services and uh so how to how do how do
you uh you know how do you conduct the
advantages
and the innocent advantages and their
consumers so you know that is one you
know aspect we have to handle you know
instead of telling that we will not
allow anyone instead of that can we
brought in some sort of consent
mechanism and I'm very happy to state
that you know Pride recently has now
introduced consent mechanism and that
now is you know being implemented and
next two three years another
implementation will be completed in this
sense that people will take the consent
if they want to send the uh you know
send any kind of uh you know
advertisement or message or information
to you for example an architect now the
architect may be interested in some
aspect related to architectural products
or information so you know that then you
know then you know the you know the
consent if he's you know he or she is
giving then you know I think you know
that that spam should be allowed but the
other thing you know um but if you don't
want that then it can shift if not given
then if you stand there there has to be
guarantee that they have already
provided this this is one thing but
one big problem is that of you know
turbulent activities that includes you
know uh you know identities act that
also includes Financial thoughts these
are the two things you know which we
should be buried and we have come out
with now uh I know our detailed HTC
guidelines and uh uh we also now you
know uh have uh you know got one uh
separate uh
telephone series that is called 141. so
you know the you know transaction tell
me one line so all the banks and all the
financial institutions or all other
people you know they have actually went
uh want to send some message they will
be taking this particular Series so you
know that you know for example you are a
customer of a bank you will know that
you know this is the number which comes
from the bank and you will not pick up
any other number even if it's poisoning
as a bank so you know then you know
that's the 10 number uh nuisance you
know can be reduced that is one thing
second you know we have as a CNN that is
in a caller name display that is you
know foreign
reduction problem is that of you know 10
number so that you know we need to work
a lot it is a continuous struggle that
is
[Music]
foreign
has been working extensively on has been
the 5G rolled out we've seen the auction
and we've seen the fastest 5G rollout
can you give us a sense as to what is
the next step forward in terms of we've
seen the rule out what is the next step
for 5G adoption one aspect being some of
the devices are quite expensive so how
do we enable this adoption of 5G going
forward yeah very good question you know
actually in India though was slightly
late compared to the other countries you
know now today we are the second largest
subscriber base as RS 5G is concerned
and the try was very careful when they
come in division he actually
recommendation itself handles the aspect
of Iran how how do you make uh the the
technology which are based on 5G
available to the you know common name so
you know we have recommended that that
every vertical Ministry should actually
prepare a plan on three things one you
know the the digital literacy on the new
technology is
enter for example you know providing
digital panels so and so on right that's
it that worked firstly then second thing
was you know how can you provide them
affordable connectivity so no
connectivity again I think you know we
think that dot alone cannot handle this
I think vertical Ministry should come so
we are recommended Administration also
particular plans for this and third
which is very very important and I think
you know most uh critical aspect of 5G
and the related technology is you know
to developing use cases and applications
lot of use cases can be you know can be
developed which can be very very useful
to the farmers for your students and the
laborers and many other people you know
so so who you know this kind of you know
lot of work is being done in India a lot
of research institutions are there if a
particular Ministry is joining if they
have some sort of a you know a formal
Arrangement whereby they will uh you
know invite the startups and the
researchers and academicians with ideas
and when you know once the ideas are
come and then you know develop those
into use cases and then you know
masculate and give to the stakeholders
Farmers students fishermen you know you
know reasonable cost then you know they
will be benefited their productivity
increase and they will be able to you
know to join the you know the mainstream
of the digital economy and this is what
our concern is most important another
thing is we have recommended and a lot
of work has been done by the government
accepted our recommendation they have
found inter ministerial working group
dot is now started working with all the
Ministries how the 5G technology can be
you know deployed by the concern
Industries Pride itself is working with
the many Industries and we are working
with them and we are helping them how
they should go about you know and you
know in implementing the recommendation
which we made one more thing important
is amazing see what is happening
what is happening in 5G uh
you know the industry 4.0 is a concept
which is becoming very very uh you know
popular so in this you know with the
help of AI air we are and Muslim to
machine you know actually you you know
you convert your industry pack and
machine way into uh you know into a you
know digitalized kind of uh you know
system so that actually
reduces cost some people say this will
reduce the you know power requirement
this will reduce the this will reduce
the base stage this will also increase
the productivity and the cost the
reduction may be 15 to 17 as you
understand of new Industries big service
providers Nursery sector they will go
for this what about amazing so we have
you know we have recommended that there
should be survey by the msme ministry of
the vertical Minister the vertical
Industries what kind of adoption of
digital uh you know technology is there
and then they should prepare a plan
again to you know provide them devices
connectivity and you know use cases so
that you know they can also take benefit
of the new technology it's a very big
word and I'm sure that you know
government will be working on that so 5G
you know unless there is see this the
two models one is that trickle down our
technology will be there people will
take I think in Western countries that
will work but uh you know we we we think
that in India you know considering use
uh the base of you know msme it is
required that there should be a
government intervention in uh saying
that you know the 5G Technologies are
adopted by the people that is more
important people and Industry both
one of the recommendations that had come
out a while back from the tra I had been
on regulation of AI I think that is the
buzzword everyone is talking about it we
saw uh conversations being had in U.S
Capitol Hill where the titles of the
tech industry the likes of Elon Musk
Mark Zuckerberg we whether your sense on
what an ideal regulatory framework will
look like the reason I ask you is
because one of the U.S senators Senator
Blumenthal had recommended that perhaps
there needs to be a harm based mechanism
where the harm that is caused by the AI
to the company for that the air tool is
held liable what is this a framework
that is workable or is there a different
framework that you would back for see
see it you know we were looking at the
AIC slash three years but you know not
that was not much clarity as soon as
things became clear and as soon as you
IG was implemented you know AI became
you know it became a you know thing
which was started being used so you know
we studied a lot of research and
according to us you know it has
opportunities and it has threats also
let us be very clear and if you can
handle the threats I think you know
there are immense opportunity and a
country like India which is a huge
skills both you know and the United
States and digital skills and we can be
the world leader when it comes to you
know Ai and even I think metaverse you
know meta version here we are we can be
the world leader so so you know uh one
should not Sun the new technology one
should rather look at how this
technology can be uh you know harnessed
and used in a way that you know the
threats can be minimized like no you
know trades cannot be completely wiped
out but it can be minimized so what we
have recommended is that that AI is
welcome
however it has a lot of threats
and we need not regulate each and every
AI use cases every AI application we
should approach the you know we should
uh you know rather adopt because this
taste you know regulation so you know
there you know that and that requires a
lot of you know deliberation a lot of
understanding and you know a lot of
collaboration with the industry itself
you know consultation with the industry
and there you know then then if she can
decide if these are the AI which can
have adverse impact applications or you
know this kind of adverse impact on the
society on the economy or the security
of the nation I think you know those are
the ASB scans so uh and and that that
way uh and but that you know again the
question of some sort of international
collaboration because you know AI is a
new technology you know one thing which
we should remember the borderless you
know everything is borderless so AI a
lot we will not be able to regulate it
so you know India you know G20 for
example you know this issue was taken up
in a very big manner by vulnerable prime
minister also and uh you know India
being such a big country and the way we
are you know doing great when it comes
to you know digitalization of the
country and economics right we can take
the leadership and we can you know push
we should push for the some sort of you
know some International mechanism so
that you know what action we take here
also you know the same thing is not
mirrored by the other countries
and we wish you the very best uh not
just uh for the next few days but also
as you move ahead and we hope that you
stay in touch and you allow us an
opportunity to stay connected into again
ask you more questions always an
engaging experience thank you thank you
very much I'm sure you know that it's
very nice to interact with